Guide to the James S. Trefil papers, 1965-2009
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
James S. Trefil papers
1965-2009
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
James S. Trefil, 1938-
C0084
58 linear feet (116 boxes)
Collection contains materials pertaining to the research and career of Dr. Trefil. Types of materials include correspondence, research notes, notes from courses both taken and taught, book manuscripts, and information pertaining to conferences he attended.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by James Trefil in 2003 and 2011.
Biographical Information
Physicist and author James S. Trefil is known for his writing and his interest in teaching science to nonscientists. He is a Fellow of the APS and a former Guggenheim Fellow. His numerous books and articles include works written for general audiences. He co-authored The Dictionary of Cultural Literacy (3rd ed., 2002) and in 1992 published The Facts of Life (Harold Morowitz, co-author). Science Matters: Achieving Scientific Literacy, was co-authored with Robert Hazen in 1991, and in 1995 they published The Sciences: An Integrated Approach. Dr. Trefil's A Scientist in the City appeared in 1994. Are We Unique: A Scientist Explores the Complexity of the Human Brain appeared in 1997. The National Geographic Society published his book Other Worlds: The Solar System and Beyond in 1999. He was the general editor of The Encyclopedia of Science and Technology (2002) and co-author of Good Seeing: a Scientific History of the Carnegie Institution. His most recent book is The Laws of Nature (2002). He is a regular contributor to Smithsonian Magazine and was previously University Professor and Professor of Physics at the University of Virginia. In 2000 American Institute of Physics chose him to receive the Andrew W. Gemant Award, presented for outstanding and sustained contributions in bridging the gap between science and society. During 2003-2004, he was a Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholar.
Scope and Content
Collection contains materials pertaining to the research and career of Dr. Trefil. Types of materials include correspondence, research notes, notes from courses both taken and taught, book manuscripts, and information pertaining to conferences he attended.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged both alphabetically by subject and chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Trefil, James S., 1938-
Subjects:
Science--Study and teaching (Higher)--United States.
Contents List
- James Trefil papers
  - Mind of God- 1st Draft- Introduction (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- 1st Draft- Chapters 4 Through 15 (Folder 1-13, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Introduction (Folder 14, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 1 "In an English Orchid" (Folder 15, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 2 "Halley and His Comet" (Folder 16, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 3 "Science in Context" (Folder 17, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 4 "Reading the Mind of God" (Folder 18, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 5 " The Glassmakers of Benediktbeuren" (Folder 19, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 6 "Atoms and Light" (Folder 20, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 7 "The Discovery of Helium: A Crisis for Universality" (Folder 21, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 8 "What Else is in the Sun?" (Folder 22, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 9 "The Discovery of Deep Time" (Folder 23, Box 1)
  - Mind of God- Edited 1st Draft- Chapter 12 "The Nucleus" (Folder 24, Box 1)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Edited Introduction and Index (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Edited Chapters 1 through 6 (Folder 2-7, Box 2)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Chapter 7 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Edited Chapter 8 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Chapter 9 (Folder 10, Box 2)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Edited Chapters 10 Through 15 (Folder 11-16, Box 2)
  - Proposal "Reading the Mind of God" (Folder 17, Box 2)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Prologue (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 1 "Expanding Horizons, Shrinking Earth" (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 2 "Discovering the Galaxies" (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 3 "The Big Bang" (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - Dark Side- Revised Draft- Chapter 4 "Five Reasons Why Galaxies Can't Exist" (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 5 "Bubbles and Superclusters" (Folder 6, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Interlude (Folder 7, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 7 "How Dark Matter Could Solve the Structure Problem of the Universe" (Folder 8, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 8 "Dark Matter and Missing Mass: How Much Should There Be?" (Folder 9, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 9 "Candidates For Dark Matter" (Folder 10, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 10 "The Massive Neutrino Caper" (Folder 11, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 11 "Is the Universe Controlled by Wimps? Exotic Candidates for Dark Matter" (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 12 "Cosmic Strings: Solution or Snake Oil?" (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 14 "The Fate of The Universe" (Folder 14, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 13 "Experimental Searches for Dark Matter" (Folder 15, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 10 "The Age of the Earth" (Folder 16, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 11 "Models, Reality, and the Arrogance of Theoretical Physicists" (Folder 17, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 12 "The Nucleus" (Folder 18, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 13 "The Age of Stars" (Folder 19, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 14 "The Expanding Universe: A Choice of Miracle" (Folder 20, Box 3)
  - Darkside- Revised Draft- Chapter 15 "Creation: The Ultimate Test" (Folder 21, Box 3)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Front Cover and Introductory Material (Folder 1, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 1 "Meditations at Sunset" (Folder 2, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 2 "Of Clocks and Calenders" (Folder 3, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 3 "Spots on the Sun" (Folder 4, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 5 "Clouds" (Folder 5, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 6 "When Clouds Go Bad" (Folder 6, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 7 "Whatever Happened to Hurricane Zelda?" (Folder 7, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 8 "When the Water Won't Boil" (Folder 8, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 9 "Colors in the Sky" (Folder 9, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 10 "Roses Are Red, But What About Geraniums?" (Folder 10, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 11 "The Scale of Things, or Why You Can't Get a Suntan Through a Window" (Folder 11, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 12 "Lightning Bolts and Life" (Folder 12, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 4 "When the Sunspots Disappeared" (Folder 13, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 13 "Lightning Rods and the Research Pipeline" (Folder 14, Box 4)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Original Edited Draft- Chapter 14 "Ball Lightning, UFO's, and Other Strange Things in the Sky" (Folder 15, Box 4)
  - Pergamon Correspondence- Hydrodynamics and Solds Text (Folder 1, Box 5)
  - Heat Loss Article (Folder 2, Box 5)
  - Wood Article- S.M. (Folder 3, Box 5)
  - Americana (Folder 4, Box 5)
  - Chimney (Folder 5, Box 5)
  - Scientific Truth Essay (Folder 6, Box 5)
  - Smithsonian (Folder 7, Box 5)
  - LAP Text Correspondence (Folder 8, Box 5)
  - Stove Efficiency (Folder 9, Box 5)
  - Fluidized Bed Proposal (Folder 10, Box 5)
  - Astronomy (Folder 11, Box 5)
  - Nation (Folder 12, Box 5)
  - Elementary Particles (OMNI) (Folder 1, Box 6)
  - Bee Keeping (Originals) (Folder 2, Box 6)
  - Grolier/Quarks (Folder 3, Box 6)
  - Hot Water Insulation (Folder 4, Box 6)
  - Wiring- M.E.N. (Folder 5, Box 6)
  - Tachyon- S.M. (Folder 6, Box 6)
  - Four and S.M. (Folder 7, Box 6)
  - Particle Therapy (Folder 8, Box 6)
  - General Relativity (Folder 9, Box 6)
  - Second Look (Folder 10, Box 6)
  - Sciences (Folder 11, Box 6)
  - Analog (Folder 12, Box 6)
  - Lightening (Folder 13, Box 6)
  - Fluid Dynamics Report (Folder 1-2, Box 7)
  - Solar (Folder 3, Box 7)
  - Conserving Electricity- Science Year (Folder 4, Box 7)
  - Science 80 (1980)- P Decay (Folder 5, Box 7)
  - Outter Matter- Science 80 (1981) (Folder 6, Box 7)
  - Insulation/Science Year (Folder 7, Box 7)
  - Sun (Folder 8, Box 7)
  - Velikovsky (Folder 9, Box 7)
  - Science 83 (Folder 10, Box 7)
  - S.M.- Vacuum (Folder 11, Box 7)
  - Brittanica (Folder 12, Box 7)
  - Photographs (Folder 13, Box 7)
  - Superconductivity- S.M. (Folder 1, Box 8)
  - Science Year (Folder 2, Box 8)
  - World Book (Folder 3, Box 8)
  - Composite Particles- Loki (Folder 4, Box 8)
  - Photos- "Unexpected Venture" (Folder 5, Box 8)
  - Photos (Folder 6, Box 8)
  - Photos- "Moment of Creation" (Folder 7, Box 8)
  - Figures for "Moment of Creation"- Figs A 58 (152 Pieces) (Folder 8, Box 8)
  - Photos (10,000 Feet) (Folder 9, Box 8)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Artwork- Chapters 1, 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, and 13 (Folder 10-19, Box 8)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Line Edited Prologue and Chapter 1 (Folder 20, Box 8)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Line Edited Chapters 2 through 14 (Folder 21-33, Box 8)
  - Dark Side of the Universe- Index (Folder 34, Box 8)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Line Edited Illustration Chart and Introduction (Folder 1, Box 9)
  - Reading the Mind of God- Line Edited Chapters 1 through 15 and Epilogue (Folder 2-16, Box 9)
  - Dark Side of the Universe- Edited (Folder 17, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Table of Contents (Folder 18, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Correspondence (Folder 19, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Introduction and Prologue (Folder 20, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 1 Expanding Horizons, Shrinking Earth (Folder 21, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 2 Discovering the Galaxies (Folder 22, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 3 The Big Bang (Folder 23, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 5 The Galaxy Problem: Defining the Parameters (Folder 24, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 7 Bubbles in the Void (Folder 25, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 8 The Scale of Things (Folder 26, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 8, Revised Table of Contents (Folder 27, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 9 Dark Matter vs Missing Mass (Folder 28, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 10 Candidates for Dark Matter (Folder 29, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 11 The Massive Neutrinocaper (Folder 30, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 11, Revised Table of Contents (Folder 31, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 13, Revised Table of Contents (Folder 32, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 14, Revised Table of Contents (Folder 33, Box 9)
  - The Dark Side of the Universe- Draft- Chapter 15 Cosmic Strings: Solution or Snake Oil (Folder 34, Box 9)
  - Science Matters- STGPS, Chapter Notes and Comments, Introduction Drafts, Uncorrected Proof, and Index Draft (Folder 1-5, Box 10)
  - Science Matters- Research and Chapter Drafts (Folder 6, Box 10)
  - Science Matters- Research and Chapter Drafts (Folder 7, Box 10)
  - Science Matters- Legal Contract (Folder 1, Box 11)
  - Science Matters- Publicity Articles (Folder 2, Box 11)
  - Science Matters- New York Times Articles (Folder 3-4, Box 11)
  - Science Matters- Doubleday Publication Correspondence (Folder 5, Box 11)
  - Science Matters- Publicity (Folder 6-7, Box 11)
  - A Scientist in the City- First Draft- Chapters 1 through 16 (Folder 8-23, Box 11)
  - A Scientist in the City- Skyscrapers, Systems, Glass, Sears Tower, Fiber Optics/Communications, Energy, Transport, Edge Cities, End, Fiber Optics, and Miscellaneous (Folder 1-11, Box 12)
  - Neanderthal- Notes (Folder 12-13, Box 12)
  - B Quark- Discover Magazine (Folder 14, Box 12)
  - Magazine Articles 1986-1995 (Folder 1, Box 13)
  - Neanderthal- Mysteries of Life and the Universe (Folder 2, Box 13)
  - Astronomy Book- Notes (Folder 3, Box 13)
  - Astronomy- Correspondence (Folder 4, Box 13)
  - The Facts of Life: Science and the Abortion Controversy- Preliminary Draft (Folder 5-6, Box 13)
  - Correspondence 1989-1991 (Folder 1, Box 14)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company Text (Folder 2, Box 14)
  - Scribner Contract and Correspondence (Folder 3-4, Box 14)
  - UVA Copyright Policy (Folder 5, Box 14)
  - 1001 Things- Correspondence (Folder 6, Box 14)
  - 1001 Things- Permissions (Folder 7, Box 14)
  - 1001 Things (Folder 8-9, Box 14)
  - Smithsonian Institution- Book Series Proposal (Folder 1, Box 15)
  - WNET (Folder 2, Box 15)
  - National Research Council (Folder 3, Box 15)
  - General Physics (Folder 4, Box 15)
  - Anti-Matter (Folder 5-6, Box 15)
  - Great Ideas in Science- Course Proposal and Lecture Notes (Folder 7, Box 15)
  - AAAS Report 1990 (Folder 1-2, Box 16)
  - AAAS Report (Lederman's) 1990 Letter (Folder 3-5, Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous Topics in Theoretical Physics- Berman Weak Int. (Folder 6-7, Box 16)
  - Lecture Notes (Folder 8, Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous Topics in Theoretical Physics- Dispersion Theory Seminar (Folder 1, Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Topics in Theoretical Physics- Density Matrix, SU3 (Folder 2, Box 17)
  - Multiple Scattering From Light Nuclei (Folder 3, Box 17)
  - Photoproduction From Light Nuclei II (Folder 4-5, Box 17)
  - History of Science Seminars (Folder 6, Box 17)
  - Physics 205E (Folder 7-9, Box 17)
  - Incoherent Production and Duality- Duality and VMP (Folder 1, Box 18)
  - Incoherent Production and Duality- Incoherent Production (Folder 2, Box 18)
  - N* Excitations (Chains) (Folder 3, Box 18)
  - Unified Field Theory (Folder 4, Box 18)
  - GUT Monopole- Papers (Folder 5, Box 18)
  - GUT Monopole- Talk Notes (Folder 6, Box 18)
  - GUT Monopole- Plasma and Sun (Folder 7, Box 18)
  - GUT Monopole- Bound States (Folder 8, Box 18)
  - GUT Monopole- Ionization 1 (Folder 9, Box 18)
  - Cosmology and Astronomy (Folder 10, Box 18)
  - Meditations at Sunset (Folder 1, Box 19)
  - Meditations at Sunset- Chapters 1, 2, 3, 4, 9, 12, 13, 14 (Folder 1-10, Box 19)
  - Scientist at the Seashore (1st Draft)- Introduction (Folder 11, Box 19)
  - Scientist at the Seashore (1st Draft)- Chapters 1 through 15 (Folder 12-25, Box 19)
  - Scientist at the Seashore (Rough Draft)- Introduction (Folder 26, Box 19)
  - Scientist at the Seashore (Rough Draft)- Chapters 1 through 4 (Folder 27-30, Box 19)
  - Scientist at the Seashore (Rough Draft)- Chapters 5 through 14 (Folder 1-10, Box 20)
  - 1001 Things- Miscellaneous Draft Papers (Folder 11-13, Box 20)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- The Formation of the Earth- Plate Tectonics- Geological Features of the Earth- Rocks and Minerals- The Earth's Water- The Atmosphere, Weather, and Climate (Folder 1-6, Box 21)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- Ecosystems- Molecules of Life- The Genetic Code- The Structure of the Cell- The Division of Cells- Plants- Plant Reproduction (Folder 7-13, Box 21)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- Animals- How Animals Are Put Together- Animal Reproduction and Development- Classification of Living Things- Ideas About the Origins of Life- Single Celled Organisms- Human Evolution (Folder 14-20, Box 21)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- Evolution- Evolution of Complex Life- Dinosaurs- Creationism and Evolution- Common Misconceptions About Evolution- Controversies in Evolution (Folder 21-26, Box 21)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- What is a Human Being?- Stars- Galaxies- Cosmology- Classical Optics- Waves- Electromagnetic Radiation- Magnetism- Electricity- Measurments of Time (Folder 27-36, Box 21)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- Gravity- Classical Mechanics- The Electronic Properties of Matter- The Nucleus of the Atom and Radioactivity- Quantum Optics (Folder 37-41, Box 21)
  - 1001 Things (1st Revision)- Chaos- Quantum Mechanics- Special and General Relativity- Chemistry- A Glossary of Chemical Terms- Molecular Hall of Fame (Folder 42-47, Box 21)
  - PEP Study (Folder 1, Box 22)
  - Table on P-A Scattering (Folder 2, Box 22)
  - Quark Seminar (Folder 3, Box 22)
  - Seminar Notes (Folder 4, Box 22)
  - The College of William and Mary in Virginia (Folder 5, Box 22)
  - Second Berkeley File (Folder 6, Box 22)
  - Notes for Montreal Talk (Folder 7, Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Folder 8, Box 22)
  - Chicago, 1974 (APS) (Folder 9, Box 22)
  - Berkeley Conference (Folder 10, Box 22)
  - Med. Phys. Lecture (Folder 11, Box 22)
  - RPC Talk (Folder 12, Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 13, Box 22)
  - Seminar Notes (Folder 14, Box 22)
  - Washington, 1975 (Folder 1-2, Box 23)
  - ERICE (Folder 3, Box 23)
  - Urology Proposal, 1972 (Folder 4, Box 23)
  - Birmingham Meeting, 1977 (Folder 5, Box 23)
  - VCU Workshop/ Longwood (Folder 6, Box 23)
  - Bulletin of the American Physical Society, Vol.22, No.1, January 1977 (Folder 7, Box 23)
  - Bulletin of the American Physical Society, Vol.24, No.3, March 1979 (Folder 8, Box 23)
  - Bulletin of the American Physical Society, Vol.24, No.4, April 1979 (Folder 9, Box 23)
  - LASL Trip (Folder 10, Box 23)
  - Vanderbilt Conference (Folder 1, Box 24)
  - NSF Committee (Folder 2, Box 24)
  - Bulletin of the American Physical Society, Series II, Vol.17., No.1, 1972 (Folder 3, Box 24)
  - Washington Meeting, 1971 (Folder 4, Box 24)
  - Collog. (Folder 5, Box 24)
  - [Notes and Transparencies] (Folder 6, Box 24)
  - JPP Seminar (Folder 7, Box 24)
  - GRE in Graduate Admissions (Folder 8, Box 24)
  - Wisconsin Conference (Folder 9, Box 24)
  - New York Conference (Folder 10, Box 24)
  - NAL Conference (Folder 11, Box 24)
  - Records (Folder 12, Box 24)
  - Seminars (Folder 13, Box 24)
  - Stanford Meeting (Folder 14, Box 24)
  - Manchester Conference (Folder 15, Box 24)
  - MIT Termination (Folder 16, Box 24)
  - Birmingham Meeting (Folder 17, Box 24)
  - Stoney Brook Conference (Folder 18, Box 24)
  - EERN Seminar Notes (Folder 1, Box 25)
  - Herzeg Novi School (Folder 2, Box 25)
  - Gait Proposal (Folder 3, Box 25)
  - Parton Model (Folder 4, Box 25)
  - Leaflet Problem (Folder 5, Box 25)
  - UDS Proposal 1970 (Folder 6, Box 25)
  - AEC Proposal October 1972 (Folder 7, Box 25)
  - Research Corp 1972 (Folder 8, Box 25)
  - Notes (Summer 1971) (Folder 9, Box 25)
  - VPI Symposium (Folder 10, Box 25)
  - Moment of Creation (1st Draft)- Introduction (Folder 1, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (1st Draft)- Chapters 1 through 15 (Folder 1-18, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (Edited Draft)- Notes on Title and Photos (Folder 19, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (Edited Draft)- Title Page and Table Contents (Folder 20, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (Edited Draft)- Introduction and Introduction to Part I (Folder 21, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (Edited Draft)- Chapters 1 through 15 (Folder 22-38, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (Edited Draft)- Glossary (Folder 39, Box 26)
  - Moment of Creation (Edited Draft)- Index (Folder 40, Box 26)
  - The Unexpected Vista (1st Draft)- Table of Contents (Folder 1, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (1st Draft)- Introduction (Folder 2, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (1st Draft)- Parts I through XII (Folder 3-14, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (Edited Draft)- Title Page (Folder 15, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (Edited Version)- Introduction (Folder 16, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (Edited Draft)- Parts I through XII (Folder 17-28, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (Edited Draft)- Index (Folder 29, Box 27)
  - The Unexpected Vista (Edited Draft)- Description of Photos (Folder 30, Box 27)
  - Physics 101- Outline (Folder 1, Box 28)
  - Physics 101- Introduction- Egyptians, Babylonians, Phases of the Noon- Greeks- The Flowering and Death of Greek Science- The Copernican Revolution- Scientific Method- The Newtonian World (Folder 2-8, Box 28)
  - Physics 101- Electricity and Magnetism- Exams and Notes- 1977- 1976- 1S- 1975 (Folder 9-14, Box 28)
  - Bibliography 1970-83- Nature 1977-83 (Folder 1-2, Box 29)
  - Physics 102- Relativity- The Atom- Atomic Structure- Quantum Mechanics- Nuclear Physics- Radioactivity- Hoxton Lecture (Folder 3-10, Box 29)
  - Correspondence- 1967-68, 1969-70, 1970-71, 1971-72, 1972-73 (Folder 1-6, Box 30)
  - Correspondence 1973-74 (Folder 1-2, Box 31)
  - Correspondence 1974-75 (Folder 3-4, Box 31)
  - Correspondence 1975-76 (Folder 5, Box 31)
  - New York Times Magazine (Folder 1, Box 32)
  - New Physics (Folder 2, Box 32)
  - 1001 Things File (Folder 3, Box 32)
  - Berman Lectures (Folder 4, Box 32)
  - Simple Harmonic Motion and Waves (Folder 5, Box 32)
  - Lectures on Glauber (Folder 6, Box 32)
  - Writer Talk (Folder 7, Box 32)
  - Time-Life/Sun (Folder 8, Box 32)
  - The Facts of Life- Oxford University Press Kit (Folder 9, Box 32)
  - FPA Conference (Folder 10, Box 32)
  - Oxford University Press (Folder 11, Box 32)
  - The Chronicle of Higher Education (Folder 12, Box 32)
  - Roemer Talk (Folder 13, Box 32)
  - Novel Notes (Folder 14, Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous- University of Chicago (Folder 15, Box 32)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship (Folder 16, Box 32)
  - End of Science Book Proposal (Folder 17, Box 32)
  - Center for Advanced Studies (Folder 18, Box 32)
  - ZBC Memos (Folder 19, Box 32)
  - Meetings: ETI, Non Linear Dynamics, SPSS, AAAS (Folder 20, Box 32)
  - Meetings (Folder 1, Box 33)
  - APS Meetings (Folder 2, Box 33)
  - Research Proposal Submitted to the National Science Foundation (Folder 3, Box 33)
  - Mult. Scatlering (Folder 4, Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Physics (Folder 5, Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Non Physics (Folder 6, Box 33)
  - Lecture Notes (Folder 7, Box 33)
  - General Education Working Group (Folder 8, Box 33)
  - Smithsonian Book Series (Folder 9, Box 33)
  - Glauber Theory (Folder 10, Box 33)
  - 1988 NPR/AAAS Meeting (Folder 11, Box 33)
  - Stonybrook and Wisconsin Conference (Folder 12, Box 33)
  - November 1987 (Folder 13, Box 33)
  - Crater Talk (Folder 14, Box 33)
  - Monopole Seminar (Folder 15, Box 33)
  - Science Matters- Book World (Folder 16, Box 33)
  - Book Reviews (Folder 17, Box 33)
  - Living in Space (Edited Draft)- Introduction (Folder 1, Box 34)
  - Living in Space (Edited Draft)- Chapters 1 through 12 (Folder 2-13, Box 34)
  - Living in Space (Edited Version)- Figures 1-12 and 2 Drawings (Folder 14, Box 34)
  - Living in Space (Edited Draft)- Photos Herewith (Folder 15, Box 34)
  - Trefil Lineart 104 Pieces (Folder 16, Box 34)
  - N.Y. Times- SSC Article (Folder 1-5, Box 35)
  - Greenhouse/SM (Folder 1, Box 36)
  - Greenhouse/SM- [SM/Climate Modeling] (Folder 2, Box 36)
  - Greenhouse/SM- [Nuclear Winter] (Folder 3-5, Box 36)
  - Consumers Guide to Pseudosciences (Folder 1, Box 37)
  - Science Digest Toys (Folder 2, Box 37)
  - Cold Fusion (Folder 3, Box 37)